what's up my piano friends zacchaeus
here today i'm going to teach you the
top four
exercises for piano beginners your own
piano technique workout plan
four simple yet powerful exercises to
develop your finger strength
flow control and effortlessness on the
keys
if you have any of these issues you know
sloppy choppy tone hand independence
issues
weak in feeble playing or if it just
seems like my hands don't want to
cooperate these exercises
will just take care of these once and
for all and give you that beautiful
smooth effortless confidence on the keys
to develop the muscle memory to play the
songs you love and surprise your friends
and family with your beautiful plank
maybe even bring a tear to their eye
section one i'm going to teach you
exactly which notes to play
section two is important i'm going to
teach you the proper movement patterns
so you don't drill in bad habits that
are an absolute nightmare to correct in
the future and section three is the fun
part
simple tricks to learn these easier and
faster using the science of how our
brains work to work smarter
not harder and people who use these
strategies learn an average of four to
ten times faster than those who don't i
literally taught this to adult beginners
all over the world and even gave a ted
talk on it so if you're struggling on
piano you're in the right place
alright let's get started alright so
step one
is learning the notes now this exercise
works on the principle
of hitting every two note finger
combination
so basically if we label our fingers one
through five with our one being thumb
and our five being pinky
if we start from finger one which is
your thumb there are only
four options we have right we can go
from one to two
we can go from one to three we can go
from one to four
or one to five where there's literally
no other options i can play from here
and same thing if we start on finger two
right we have four
options we can go two to one we can go
two to three we can go two to four
or we can go two to five that's the only
place we can go
from finger two same with finger number
three right three
one three two three four
three five and the same the exact same
principle
applies to fingers number four and five
so as you can see
there's only a total of 20 possible
finger combinations
in all of music and if you can get all
these two note combinations
sounding smooth and strong and powerful
with good technique
you can play any finger combination out
there
so for example let's say you have a song
that goes you know
one two three five one maybe it's a
melody like
something like that right well guess
what this is just a combination of
one two two three
three five five one
one two three five one so if you have
all these two note combinations sounding
good with the finger gauntlet exercise
all you have to do is essentially put
them together and you already have
the muscle memory drilled in for the
song that you're working on so here's
how you actually do
the finger gauntlet exercise so first we
start with our thumb and we play through
all the first finger
combinations so one two one
three one four one five
then we do the same thing we work the
second finger combination so
two one two three two
four two five then we take the third
finger combinations
so three one three two
three four three five
and then the fourth finger four one
four two four three four
five and then the fifth finger five one
five two five three five
four and that's it takes about a minute
remember there's a downloadable cheat
sheet
with all the notes and everything you're
gonna need from this
lesson so that way right now you can
just focus 100 of your attention
on the video so once we do this
hopefully you guys can see
how this is the only exercise you need
for finger strength and independence
because we're literally hitting every
single
finger combination now most technique
books like you know hanon and stuff
they'll give you like 20 different
exercises that accomplish the exact same
thing
that we accomplished with this one
exercise so the finger gauntlet as you
can see
it's a great kind of bang for your buck
exercise you're going to reap a lot of
rewards just from learning
this one exercise now that will step on
the notes
on to step number two this is a step
most videos
will not teach you the movement pattern
now make sure please please please pay
attention
to this part this is the most important
step
because you don't want to drill in bad
habits here
and the key to this the key is to stop
focusing on the notes
and start focusing on the movement
pattern
so check this out it's simple body
mechanics really if you take a look at
your hand
you'll notice your fingers are all
different sizes right your thumb
and your pinky are significantly shorter
than your middle three fingers
so if we line up our hand on the
keyboard and if we use a straight wrist
right which is bad technique we'll talk
about that later you'll notice
your second third and fingers third and
fourth fingers are nice and curved right
they have this nice strong
curved position but your pinky if you
curve it
it's gonna fall off the edge of the keys
you won't be able to play the keys so
you literally have to have
a flat pinky just to reach the notes
and guess what a flat pinky is never
going to be strong and it's never going
to be powerful it's never going to sound
good but check this out all we have to
do to fix this simple issue
is rotate our wrist down and to the
outside
whenever we play our pinky and now look
at my pinky
right it's nice and curved as this nice
strong
curved motion and all i did was rotate
my wrist down and out so here's the
basic rule
anytime you're playing toward your pinky
you move your wrist
down and out and anytime you play toward
your thumb
you move your wrist up and in like this
and hopefully you can actually hear how
strong and even the playing is
through my fingers now if you look at it
you know if i try to play with a
straight wrist
it's going gonna get weaker as it goes
up if i curve my if i use the wrist
motion
you can say it's almost like i'm playing
the notes with my wrist
and i'm just catching the notes with my
fingers and that way
you're playing all the notes with one
motion with your wrist which makes it
sound nice and smooth
instead of playing individual notes with
each finger which is going to make it
sound
choppy and sloppy and this is actually
one of the keys to building in flow
and getting that smooth sound like you
know when you hear a piano player
and they just seem to have the ability
to make the piano just sing
this is the technique that's allowing
them to do that all right so in order to
drill
in this over under technique into your
muscle memory what you want to do is
every time you're running a finger
gauntlet exercise make sure you're
focusing on using
the over under wrist motion all right so
let's take
just the first finger combinations for
now to make it simple so one
two one three one four
one five all right so when we go one to
two
guess what we're moving toward our pinky
right one to two
so we rotate our wrist down and out
that's the rule right so
one two and now we go back to one so
we're gonna rotate our wrist
up and in to go back to one and then we
go to three so down and out because it's
toward our pinky
and then up and in back to one and then
down and out to four
up and into one down and out to five up
and into one
so as you can see for this particular
exercise you're basically making these
small
little circles so one two
one three one four
one five now at first when you're
practicing this exercise
you want to really exaggerate the motion
and the circles you're using so it
should look like you know
you're really exaggerating how far up
and down you're going down
because the more you exaggerate it the
more your brain
can really put it into your muscle
memory and you're giving clear
singles to your hands and to your
fingers that this is how i want you to
play
now as you get better and better and as
you start to speed this up
these circles will become smaller
because you don't have time to do giant
circles and in reality once you start
playing actual songs
these circles will be very subtle and
you might kind of barely even notice
that your wrists are making these
circles
but at the beginning when you're
training you want to exaggerate this
wrist motion once you get this motion
down
once you drill it into your muscle
memory it starts to become second nature
and it'll start happening
automatically when you play songs you
won't even have to think about it
all right on to step three and you're
absolutely going to love this part
this is everybody's favorite part the
accelerated learning technique
to learn this drill absolutely faster
basically just a fancy way of saying hey
let's work smarter not harder and get
the same result in a shorter amount of
time
and today we're going to focus on
rhythmic variations
which is my personal favorite strategy
for drilling in
muscle memory or what some people like
to call finger memory
all right so here's how it works for now
we're just going to focus on the first
finger combinations to make it
a little bit simpler for you guys and
we're going to run the finger gauntlet
through the four different rhythms all
right so first we're going to run the
finger gauntlet
through rhythm number one which is long
short
long short it sounds like this long
short long short long
short long short
next up we're going to run it through
rhythm number two which is
short long short long sounds like this
short long short long
and then next we're going to use rhythm
number three which is long
short short short sounds like this
long short short short
and finally we're going to use rhythm
number four which is short
short short long sounds like this
[Music]
and i promise you if you run this
exercise through these four rhythms
by the end of it you're gonna be amazed
how much more you
feel it in your fingers and when you go
back to normal
it's gonna feel easy it's gonna feel
like it's in your fingers
all right so does that make sense are
you starting to see how putting all
these steps together
is way more effective than just you know
repeating it over and over and
banging your head against the wall
trying to learn it you know let me know
in the comments if this if this is
really kind of opening your eyes to
what's possible on you for a piano
once you have the correct tools to learn
at this point a lot of people start
thinking
zack why don't i just practice the
finger gauntlet
like you said it has every single finger
combination you know i don't need the
rest of the stinking exercises
and please do not make this mistake do
not fall into this trap
okay remember these exercises are
designed to work together
in a system for example if you're not
practicing the relaxation exercise
you'll end up just drilling in the
finger gauntlet with a bunch of tension
and it's actually going to hurt you down
the road
and you know there are other things like
crossovers that we have to drill in with
the finger control exercise so remember
these all fit together in a plan and so
the rest of the plan i'm going to put in
four separate videos because if you want
to learn piano the right way
for each of these exercises you need to
learn the notes the form and the motion
and the accelerated learning techniques
now most youtube videos out there
they just give you the notes and they're
like good luck bucko
and all these students they form these
bad habits that absolutely kill their
technique down the road
because nobody taught them how to play
with proper technique so i need to give
you
everything you need to be successful but
that's gonna be a super long video if i
put it all here i'm gonna put a link
right here
click the link enter your name and email
hit submit and you'll go to this page
with the intro video here and the other
four videos here and i'll be releasing
one of those
every couple days you can also click
this link to get the cheat sheet for not
only this video
but it also has stuff for the other
videos in this series alright so click
the link i'll see you there and i'm
excited for you to start your piano
journey toward beautiful
effortless piano playing